<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Big Brain Ideas</title>
    <link>http://superbigbrain.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Big Brain Ideas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://superbigbrain.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 7: X-Raying a Book</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-7-x-raying-a-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-7-x-raying-a-book/</guid>
      <description>A common theme in How to Read a Book is understanding what a book is about. Adler continues building on this theme in X-Raying a Book by suggesting that we summarize the book we&amp;rsquo;re reading as briefly as possible and write our own outline for the book. Adler&amp;rsquo;s argument is that these tasks demonstrate your understanding of the logical structure of the book, which is a prerequisite for the reading skills that come later in How to Read a Book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 6: Pigeonholing a Book</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-6-pigeonholing-a-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-6-pigeonholing-a-book/</guid>
      <description>Key Ideas The primary argument of Chapter 6 is that you have to know what kind of book you&amp;rsquo;re reading to get the most out of it. Adler recommends classifying the book before you start reading. Is it fiction or non-fiction? Is it practical or theoretical?
Fiction vs. Non-Fiction Books The idea here should be obvious. If you&amp;rsquo;re reading for entertainment, then go wild. Read whatever you want. But if you&amp;rsquo;re reading to learn about politics or science or history, it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand whether you&amp;rsquo;re reading something true or something made up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 5: How to Be a Demanding Reader</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-5-how-to-be-a-demanding-reader/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 00:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-5-how-to-be-a-demanding-reader/</guid>
      <description>This will be a short one. How to Be a Demanding Reader is a short chapter, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t find many insights. It felt more like &amp;ldquo;some final thoughts before we talk about analytical reading&amp;rdquo; than anything else.
Key Ideas The TL;DR of this chapter is that you will get the most out of a book when you have a conversation with it. A common theme we keep coming back to is that reading should generate questions, and your job is to find answers in the book, and that theme is present in this chapter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Take Smart Notes: Pre-Read</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-take-smart-notes-pre-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-take-smart-notes-pre-read/</guid>
      <description>This post comes from an exercise I did to try Adler&amp;rsquo;s suggestions for systematically skim a book. I chose How to Take Smart Notes because it&amp;rsquo;s on the list of books I&amp;rsquo;m planning to read after finishing How to Read a Book.
Suggestions Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick refresher on Adler&amp;rsquo;s suggestions for how to systematically skim a book:
 Look at the title page and, if the book has one, the preface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 4: The Second Level of Reading: Inspectional Reading</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-4-the-second-level-of-reading-inspectional-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-4-the-second-level-of-reading-inspectional-reading/</guid>
      <description>First, you may notice that I skipped Chapter 3: The First Level of Reading: Elementary Reading. I skipped it because elementary reading is such a basic concept that I didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything insightful in the short chapter that talked about it. I figured our time would be better spent on more useful things.
Key Ideas The two key ideas covered in Chapter 3 are systematic skimming and superficial reading.
Systematic Skimming This makes up the bulk of my notes on the chapter because it&amp;rsquo;s less obvious than superficial reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 2: The Levels of Reading</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-2-the-levels-of-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-2-the-levels-of-reading/</guid>
      <description>Key Ideas This was a short chapter, and it revolved around a single key idea: there are four reading levels. Each level serves a different purpose, but they all work together to provide a framework for reading.
The four levels of reading are:
 Elementary Reading Inspectional Reading Analytical Reading Syntopical Reading  Level 1: Elementary Reading This is the simplest level of reading and what I think of when someone tells me they&amp;rsquo;ve read a book.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Read a Book, Chapter 1: The Activity and Art of Reading</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-1-the-activity-and-art-of-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/how-to-read-a-book-chapter-1-the-activity-and-art-of-reading/</guid>
      <description>The first chapter of How to Read a Book sets the context for the rest of the book: there are multiple ways to read a book, and some are more effective than others, depending on your goal.
If your goal is to read for entertainment, the advice in How to Read a Book will not be useful to you. If your goal is to read for information, you&amp;rsquo;ll get more than you bargained for because Adler is talking about the third type of reading that requires much more effort: reading for understanding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Up Next: How to Read a Book</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/up-next-how-to-read-a-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/up-next-how-to-read-a-book/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve always had a preference for reading books over listening to lectures. I find lectures to be slow and boring, and books allow me to choose my own pace. With books, I can also skip around and skim and jump over sections that don&amp;rsquo;t interest me and don&amp;rsquo;t seem relevant. That&amp;rsquo;s much more difficult to do with lectures, though it&amp;rsquo;s easier nowadays with many lectures being recorded and made available online.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn More, Think Better</title>
      <link>http://superbigbrain.com/learn-more-think-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://superbigbrain.com/learn-more-think-better/</guid>
      <description>I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been duped.
In 2013, I moved to Silicon Valley and started working as a software engineer to do important work that makes the world a better place. Over the next seven years, I worked at different companies on different products and projects, but they all had one thing in common: I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like my work mattered.
Now that&amp;rsquo;s not to say that no one in Silicon Valley is doing useful work.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>